It's great being here at TED.
إنه لأمرٌ رائع أن اكون هنا في مؤتمر تيد
You know, I think there might be some presentations
انتم تعلمون .. ربما هناك الكثير من المحادثات التي
that will go over my head,
ربما تلك الامور المتعلقة بالفضاء والامور التي هي أكبر من حجم الانسان
but the most amazing concepts
ولكن بالنسبة لي اجمل شيء في هذه الحياة
are the ones that go right under my feet.
هي تلك الامور الصغيرة
The little things in life,
التي تحدث من حولنا
sometimes that we forget about,
اشياء نتناساها .. وننساها
like pollination, that we take for granted.
مثل التلقيح
And you can't tell the story about pollinators --
ولا يمكن ان نتحدث عن التلقيح
bees, bats, hummingbirds, butterflies --
او الخفافيش او النحل او الفراشات
without telling the story about the invention of flowers
بدون ان نتحدث عن روعة الازهار
and how they co-evolved
وكيف استطاعت ان تتطور
over 50 million years.
على مدى الـ 50 مليون سنة الماضية
I've been filming time-lapse flowers
انا اقوم بتصوير نمو الازهار على مدى الزمن
24 hours a day, seven days a week,
طيلة اليوم .. طيلة الاسبوع
for over 35 years.
منذ 35 عاماً
To watch them move
وانا اشاهدها وهي تتحرك
is a dance I'm never going to get tired of.
وهي ترقص .. ولم اصاب بالمللل لوهلة
It fills me with wonder, and it opens my heart.
ان متابعة ذلك يملئني بالدهشة .. ويشعر قلبي باللهفة
Beauty and seduction, I believe,
والجمال والاغراء .. وانا اؤمن
is nature's tool for survival,
ان الازهار هي وسيلة الطبيعة للبقاء
because we will protect what we fall in love with.
لاننا نحمي ما نغرم به ..
Their relationship
ان علاقتهم مع الارض
is a love story that feeds the Earth.
هي علاقة حب
It reminds us that we are a part of nature,
انها تذكرنا اننا جزء من هذه الطبيعة
and we're not separate from it.
واننا لسنا بمعزل عنها
When I heard about the vanishing bees, Colony Collapse Disorder,
وعندما سمعت عن انقراض النحل وعن الخلل الذي يصيب مستعمراتهم
it motivated me to take action.
تحمست لكي أبدأ بالعمل حيال ذلك
We depend on pollinators
علينا ان نعي اننا نعتمد على المُلقحات هذه
for over a third of the fruits and vegetables we eat.
التي هي السبب في حصولنا على ثلث ما لدينا من فاكهة وخضار
And many scientists believe
والعديد من العلماء موقنون
it's the most serious issue facing mankind.
اننا نواجه مشكلة عويصة ان انقرضت هذه الكائنات
It's like the canary in the coalmine.
مثل الكناري الموجود في مناجم الفحم
If they disappear, so do we.
ان انقرضت .. انقرضنا
It reminds us that we are a part of nature
هذا يذكرنا اننا جزء من الطبيعة
and we need to take care of it.
وعلينا ان نهتم بها
What motivated me to film their behavior
وما حفزنا لتصوير هذه العملية
was something that I asked my scientific advisers:
هو شيء كنت قد سئلته للعلماء - علماء الطبيعة -
"What motivates the pollinators?"
كان " ما الذي يحفز المُلقحات للقيام بالتلقيح "
Well, their answer was,
وكانت الاجوبة ..
"It's all about risk and reward."
انه الرغبة في المخاطرة .. انه الرغبة في الانجاز
Like a wide-eyed kid, I'd say, "Why is that?"
ولكني قلت .. حسناً .. ولكن لماذا هذا أيضاً
And they'd say, "Well, because they want to survive."
ومن ثم قال البعض " لانه يريدون البقاء "
"Well, in order to reproduce."
ربما يريدون التكاثر
"Well, why?"
ولكني قلت .. حسناً .. ولكن لماذا هذا أيضاً
And I thought that they'd probably say, "Well, it's all about sex."
واعتقدت ان الجواب سوف يأتي .. ربما بسبب الرغبة الجنسية فحسب
And Chip Taylor, our monarch butterfly expert,
ولكن " تشيب تايلور" وهو خبير فراشات
he replied, "Nothing lasts forever.
قال لي " دوام الحال من المحال "
Everything in the universe wears out."
كل شيء في هذا الكون يتجدد
And that blew my mind.
وهذا أبهرني
Because I realized
لانني ادركت
that nature had invented reproduction
ان الطبيعة اخترعت التكاثر
as a mechanism for life to move forward,
كوسيلة للابقاء على نفسها عن طريق المضي قدماً
as a life force that passes right through us
كقوة محركة تنتقل عبر
and makes us a link in the evolution of life.
الاجيال عبر كل الكائنات
Rarely seen by the naked eye,
ومن النادر ان نميز
this intersection
التقاطع بين
between the animal world and the plant world
عالم الحيوان وعالم النبات
is truly a magic moment.
ولكنه في الحقيقة امرٌ رائعٌ جداً
It's the mystical moment
وسحريٌ جداً
where life regenerates itself,
ويحفز الحياة ويشعلها بصورة مميزة جداً
over and over again.
مهما كان عدد المرات التي يشاهده المرء لهذه المشاهد
So here is some nectar from my film.
وهنا سوف اعرض عليكم .. مقتطفات من فلمي الذي
I hope you'll drink, tweet
يركز على هذا الامر .. اتمنى ان تستمتعوا ..
and plant some seeds
وان تزرعوا ..
to pollinate a friendly garden.
وان تبذروا البذور .. وتلقحوا حدائقكم
And always take time to smell the flowers,
ودائماً .. توقفوا قليلاً لكي تستنشقوا رائحة الزهور ..
and let it fill you with beauty,
واسمحوا لانفسكم في الغرق في جمال ذلك
and rediscover that sense of wonder.
واعادة استكشاف حاسة الروعة التي تكمن في داخلكم
Here are some images from the film.
هاكم .. مقاطع من الفلم
(Music)
(موسيقى)
(Applause)
(تصفثيق)
Thank you.
شكراً
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you.
شكراً